welcome to Ife talks where we chat
openly with guest experts on their time
in the fitness industry and share some
tips on what we can all do to improve
[Music]
right so finally welcome onto the
podcast man taken a few years in there
but yeah of super secret stocks so I
would imagine most people listen to this
know who you are at this point but for
those who don't how did you get started
into fitness and where you are today oh
wow
um so I can do it in the roundabout way
completely because I finished uni uh
being a complete record for human being
and I just wanted to start training so I
could stop being in pain effectively
when it comes to just you know my body
hurting from standing up right for half
an hour right yeah
um and I did what everybody else does so
I went to like a really cheap Focus room
and you know it sucked because the only
person in with me there was this like
one grumpy meet available tracks of
stuff in a tupperware all day so you'll
never get any help or anything right
um
you know all the Teen Nation and
bodybuilding.com websites and everything
else so typical lab in the 20s you know
Journey basically yeah
um and it was just like you know I can't
even had fun to be fair but then after a
few months I was like this doesn't make
sense I'm not really know what I'm doing
I'm just kind of flailing you know it's
like yeah I'm trying to get a big bunch
try to lean at the same time you know
I'm not skinny like hell yeah
um so um I was just looking to do
something different
and I thought to myself I want to like
learn a skill basically I would like to
try Olympic weightlifting yeah
um I thought it looks kind of cool you
know I kind of like how those people
look as well basically I'm not really
into bodybuilding or anything like that
it just looks like something interesting
so I was looking for a gym around that
and I found like a I found a jungle
Plymouth performance dream
um and I joined the weightlifting club
that I was run by a really cool coach
called Rich kite um who I wonder what
he's doing nowadays actually I might tag
him in it
um so I trained that for like over a
year I think I was doing it three times
a week and I really enjoyed it but the
guys also were doing power lifting and
strongman
um and it was a general run by Slick and
conditioning coaches so it was a
completely different culture from what I
experienced in Nigeria and from like
people I knew who were doing like virgin
active or whatever basically yeah it was
you know a warehouse a nice State
basically you had no mirrors whatsoever
one dumbbell rack three deadlift
platforms free score tracks and some
Atlas Stones right yeah so
what am I doing here right
um but it was great because people
actually knew what they were talking
about they were very very helpful and
you know I did some Olympic lifting then
destroyment coach would come in and be
like hey do you want to pop in on a
Sunday try that with us you know so I
started doing that
um and I just kept training and I I had
you know times when I dropped off
because I was like oh I'm not getting
anywhere this is hard I'm not
progressing as fast as I would want to
again so yeah yeah
um and um one day
I was watching uh wrestling with my
girlfriend at the time and I thought to
myself I wonder if I'm strong enough to
do this if I'm actually fit enough now
bear in mind I spent like a long long
period of time at that point to start
using substances basically and being
very very unhealthy uh just you know um
I've mentioned that on my social media
before that was repeated time when I was
homeless basically and whatnot so I was
starting like below the level the
majority of the people who come into
work with me yeah yeah right yeah
um so I started doing that and I that's
when I realized that training got me
that good that I could do this and I was
shocked I was dreaming like whoa I can
run jump throw stuff and lift things and
pick up people basically right so um
that's when I really started officiating
it and I never thought about training
other people it was never never my goal
if you told me back then I'm gonna be a
person trainer I would laugh at you
um and one of my coaches still means you
know what you should try training people
because you have experience of being
coached and just kind of stuck in my
head
um my girlfriend at the time wanted to
do a personal training course and the
company that we went with was doing uh
two for the price of one okay so you
both signed up at the same time yeah so
she finished here first I did level two
I just can't finish it yeah
but um I ended up
um long story but I ended up running a
wrestling school you know they
originally started trading at a few
years after taking it over yeah and
because I was finished level two I could
like higher the space and put a ring in
it and start training people yeah just
like kind of save the place but now it's
training yeah and then um guys I was
training were like hey you're in a
really good shape could you help us and
I was like yeah I could a technique
thing can't get insured I have the level
too basically I could do like group
sessions basically or whatever
um I was hiring this like little
CrossFit gym on a weekend so I went to
speak to the owner and he said like hey
what are you paying me
um you know where the timetable is if
you're not coming if your guy is at some
point midweek in the evening and trade
them no problem just give me a free ride
um and then dream was kind of similar to
what I was used to so kettlebells tires
ropes basically what not so you know the
fun stuff yeah
um and like I knew also like from myself
that for guys needed in a raven for
performance and like for conditioning
basically that's kind of what's going to
be the most fun and kind of the most
beneficial rather than just doing bench
pressures
so we started doing that and like I
started getting in the better shape and
we've had a junior section on Sunday
mornings and parents were coming with
the kids and after a while they were
like oh those guys are getting in a
better shape hey imagine could you do
something for the parents as well okay
so I started like just randomly like
helping people here and there and that's
kind of when I started thinking like I
actually enjoy this and people do
benefit in the same way that I did
basically they actually are getting
stronger they can do more and they can
tell they are turning up to this
wrestling training and they can tell
they can move better but they have
better mobility and they can handle a
lot more you know effort basically and
whatnot and this wasn't it was normal
people just like a lot of women just
nerds basically yeah I'm a mustardness
that's normally the way isn't it yeah
yeah but you realize when you think a
little while the training is super super
nerdy so if you like being a nerd
training is excellent for it because
it's a rabbit hole with no end yeah
um and then I moved to Norwich for
wrestling because I got offered to do
this semi full-time basically 148 yellow
and then so that's why not you know how
many transitions in life you've got to
do something that you're used to watch
on TV when you were a kid right yeah
um and I thought like well I finished my
level three because PT is maybe
something I could do like part-time and
I'm not doing shows and I was so wrong
so um you know I finished my level three
started working at the gym group with
you and it was quite funny because I
nearly got fired before I even started
have I even told you that I don't think
I've had this so um if my old managers
or something
um so I already had a shift set up when
I was supposed to start and I was doing
a wrestling training camp and I tore my
uncle uh three days before I was
supposed to start I remember you
hobbling yeah yeah yeah yeah so I
completely Disturbed my ankle and I had
to email them and be like hey I won't be
able to start because I physically
cannot walk right and so they were like
oh okay no problem
um but I was dumb enough to agree to do
two days of shows an Isle of Wight with
the crew and mantle so I kept telling
everybody don't post anything on social
media because if anybody sees me I'll
get to check it for lunch uniform even
started right so about a week later I
came back and I was actually screwed
right I turned up and the managed
sitting down he was like yeah we didn't
believe you went on sleep we thought
you're already making excuses
um so I'm a tube yeah you know um and I
started I kind of thought like I have no
idea who I'm gonna be working with or
how that works one of the most
demoralizing things that one of my
friends told me because I told him like
yeah I'm gonna start trading people here
in Norwich and whatnot I used to live in
Plymouth and he goes the mutual made of
I was like oh yeah well this guy can do
this in Vision active you can definitely
do it oh my God oh my God yeah if this
is the bar yeah but this isn't gonna be
great but um you know
I started just talking to people and you
know the benefit kind of of being in a
place like this is that you have
everyone walking through right of
different shape sizes ages and
experience levels you know and whatnot
so if you want to train people then get
good at it this is the way to kind of do
it you talk as many people as possible
so um yeah yeah started really because
you were there full time from a start
basis yeah not in the sense that the gym
gave you full-time hours
and I was like I'm doing this better
yeah you were there from like eight or
six in the morning till like nine or ten
in the evenings basically every night
until you wear fully booked I used to
turn up like six ish seven-ish and stand
by the door just smile and say hello to
people yeah I selected Timothy how I
started I was super super nervous
because like I had no idea I was gonna
look like right I thought to myself in a
pretty good shape I'm not the biggest
though I'm not the most muscular drug
guy on the planet I'm not the strongest
guy ever I'll bet it's gonna be just
full of really fit really you know
amazing people then he turned out
they're not exactly the case and it also
it doesn't matter in a slightest yeah um
not in the long run that they were
released
um so yeah I've just been there every
day talking to people because I was very
uncertain of my own ability I kind of
didn't put the pressure of myself off I
need to get clients I need to get x
amount of people this week I just
thought to myself I'm gonna stop having
conversations with people so I set
myself a target of I'm gonna have two or
three conversations every day about
training with people who go there I'm
not gonna ask them to trade with me I'm
not going to offer them a session I just
want to talk to them about training and
that kind of after a couple of weeks
still being have confidence because you
know how it is when you face it to
clients see who did them some advice
you're asking for consultation and you
go so would you like to pay
yeah exactly it's such an alien thing
yeah because you're not used to it right
it's just I think it's really really
weird because I don't see this in any
other industry no I've never seen a
barber or anybody else be shy about
asking for money you know for some
reason you want to pay for this 25
pounds I guess yeah it's gonna be you
know a couple of hundred pounds a month
yeah I don't know I've never really had
a lot of money myself basically so like
I used to pay for a college
while you're in it right but then I
thought to myself man my coach was
amazing and people say um GoPro at the
gym or Butternut um he was a fitness
instructor for Royal Marines if you
remember correctly and he was an SEC
coach like a big Boxing Club basically
and he was just insane I used to play um
teams really bot slip team we had and
actually another extent of a guy called
tombardo Tom Barlow yeah he was a
multitamil champion and stuff like that
okay so very legit like really really
serious people you know so I went from
this like box stream and suddenly I'm in
this estate Warehouse basically full of
these insane athletes you know I'm like
whoa so I was thinking to myself like
can I make that much impact on someone
um but yeah turns out you can't so I had
no idea what my demographic is going to
be I thought it's going to be like last
in the younger 20s who gonna want to get
stronger they're going to be impressed
by the fact that they're big with a
massive bed right kind of works yeah
um and now you know well I've been doing
this for six years now nearly seven and
and like 80 of my kinds of women yeah
well that was one of the things I was
going to mention we had someone message
to say things to talk about and cover
with me one of the things was Fitness
around women because we were kind of
sick everyone goes through phases and
like your demographic changes but we
definitely went for a period where a
majority of our like clients were girls
basically yeah would you say I think I
already know the answer basically would
you say there's any major differences
between training guards or girls in your
experience absolutely yeah absolutely
women are way easier to work with yeah
yeah like no ego yeah no ego whatsoever
they come in they say I want to learn
and they learn they're not trying to
question you they're not trying to show
off because you guys have this weird
thing and I'm not trying to piss off
guys by the way but this is honestly a
thing right people come to you for
advice and you give them answers and
they are trying to show off as if they
knew better and it's like you couldn't
ask me for help why are you acting like
you know things you don't yeah and you
never I never had other women yeah
um and they just seem to take on the
advice a lot more basically and they ask
a lot more questions basically they
don't try to like there's a sweet thing
with Fitness as I ask people sometimes
right
before you learn how to drive did you
know how to drive right before somebody
taught your classes did you know
everything about cars no you get your
instructor exactly yeah before you when
you don't just start the engine and
drive your car into the wall right but
for some reason when it comes to like
physical fitness a lot of the guys feel
like they should know everything already
[Music]
and it's not in your DNA no right like
most of the people that we work with
don't know how to push the ass out yeah
yeah exactly and they think that they
somehow gonna understand those super
Advanced concept because this focus on
bro they watch one podcast so they
listen to an article intonation or
whatever yeah yeah um so like I do work
with a lot of very lovely dudes
um I've worked with a few guys who
started off like this and then they
realized quickly that this is another
way
um but in general I find women to be
easy to work with I know I mean it's
general rule of thumb is that guys seem
to have or feel that they have something
to prove because they're more like I've
only ever had one client throw up during
a session and it was during it was when
we're at the gym group and they were
doing those trial PT sessions so he's
come in for his free half hour first
mother met the guy all right I'm gonna
do a little bit of a warm-up on the
rower then we're gonna do some weights
and so we do we do run out right I only
want you to build up to like an rpe six
and like you can even think of it as 6
out of 10 effort or 60 or 40 left in
your tank but I don't want you maxing
out on this yeah 60 I'm not really fast
about the rest of the numbers and so he
starts gunning it on this road
getting into like 145 500 meter split
sometimes is 60 he's like yeah no it's
not but I can only tell you to do 60 if
you want to do more than you do more so
he's he's gunning it for the first
couple minutes I'm like right so this is
meant to be like a five ten minute
warm-up but I'm gonna make it near a
five based on how hard you're pushing
this and you did like four and a half
can I put in it to a toilet please I'm
like yep off you go and then they'd be
able to go out basically because he just
again just didn't want to admit what a
true 60 was to him
um I had another guy didn't throw up in
the session however he was also called
Harry and we were talking about the
difference between rpe and Reps and
Reserve but we use whatever one you want
but basically I need to judge how hard
you're working so we're trial in both
and he was doing bench press I was like
right so I want you to have about four
reps in reserve on relatively rpe six so
we load up we start empty Barber then we
load it up it's pushing and he does his
eight reps re-racks for about eight fret
was like super slow and a bit shaky yeah
yeah what's your rpe or how many reps in
reserve you got oh rp6 so you could do
four more of those he was like yeah I
was like come on man so unwrap a bar and
down it came and there it stays yeah I
was like right then we'll take this bar
off and so yeah it I've yet to have that
train any females yeah you've never
never had a little girl never uh a lot
of the time when I have a new guy coming
in
um you know they're like getting a bit
too excited and I have to slow down I
actually need to rain this in a little
bit there will be time when you can do
this no it's not yeah because you're
still failing you're still putting
yourself out of position basically you
know gonna come back to the next you can
determine your shoulder heads yeah and
it's no point there's literally no point
uh but I think it's because like I I
don't think it's like a man thing it's
just this like weird that it's just the
way Fitness is presented to us it's
completely backwards right because when
you look at the uh regardless of your
social media you're on our WebEx
magazines back in the day right it was
from the uh the body builders see the
muscle and fitness basically back in the
day when we were kids being like Oh you
need to live heavy you need to be there
for seven hours you know 11 days a week
yeah or whatever and then you kind of
switch to like oh you need to do this
like flailing around basically whatever
you do do as fast as you can yeah yeah
and you know make sure that you're
dripping sweat and you're huffing and
puffing because you need to grind to
pass like grinding into hustle and oh
god
um and it's just doesn't look that way
because it's a great way to injure
yourself and get no no results
whatsoever because that's that's not how
your body works yeah especially if you
haven't done anything like that before
right people come and they're like yeah
but what about hits and I'm like okay
can you run for 15 minutes in a steady
tempo yeah no okay so why is it yeah it
just takes a different name the high
rocks nowadays like similar thing just
don't worry about whether you can do it
very well just do as fast as you can and
get the best time as possible yeah yeah
but it's like you know like once you
know what you're doing in your press
full time right but you understand the
movements you can go okay I'm gonna do a
barber complex today I'm gonna do five
exercises back to back with the same way
about putting the barbell down yeah
isn't the best way to trade no it's in
the long run right you wouldn't program
that for someone no but you have
somebody going hey you only have half an
hour to train today I already know I'm
gonna miss out the session I'm quite
efficient with this Implement I just
want to get in and get it out and make
sure I do push pull then I scored in the
hinge yeah I'm like cool yeah put a
barbell on do a front score to do an
overhead press do another deal do up
until the row don't put the barbell down
do it four times go home yeah right but
that you need to actually know how to do
those things you need to know what your
rpe is yeah you need to pick the weight
correctly uh you still need to do your
rest breaks so you still need to
understand like what the respect is and
like you know you don't have to do 60
seconds it's absolutely fine to do 90 or
120 or even longer if you feel like it
and like people are shocked when you
tell them this oh yeah think you're
cheating if you take like a three to
five minute rest yes I know this is what
you should be doing if you're doing it
at this intensity at this rep range
exactly but it's because like when we
when we're looking at you know the
workout of the day that we see on
Instagram right it's never talked about
like the quality of movement is what
matters yeah like it's like if you just
do it everywhere by fading about you
you're not getting the right contraction
that you're looking for you're not
getting the right stimulus basically
you're probably just throwing your
joints out of position but there is also
this it has been forever you know I you
need to feel like you're working yeah
right and the truth is you will very
often not feel like you're working very
hard no you want to feel like you're out
of your comfort zone but you don't need
to be redlining everything yeah exactly
yeah so like you know and so people need
that explained that there are moments in
your trading when that's appropriate and
there are times to you know you build
your trading in phases and there will be
a time and you want to kind of push it
and then you tell people the deload
exists yeah and this is like you just
you know explain black magic to people
basically you're telling me to drop the
way to a whole week like this yeah you
will come back feeling better stronger
literally right but it never gets
explained because it's not exciting yeah
yeah like the um what I always have with
your clients and this is to the point
when I'm gonna start writing memes about
it right the stuff that breaks them the
most it's the stuff they would never get
a like on Instagram yeah it's gonna be
like the stuff of resistance bands and
you make the problem isometric called
right yeah and just like very very
simple stuff because you know the hips
aren't stable you know the ankles are
you know lining up with the knees you
know what's wobbling right so you can do
something like this yeah you demonstrate
and I go why am I paying for this and I
take that and they suddenly realized
that this is like one of the hardest
things they've ever done in their life
yeah yeah but yeah unfortunately like to
this day I see people like I've
genuinely had it a few months ago when I
was waiting for clients uh you know
scrolling for my feed and there was a
workout of the day right and then 15
minutes later I have literally seen ipt
do that workout with the client well I
remember being in my staff from the same
people scroll through and be like that
looks good I've got four sessions this
afternoon and we'll be doing that yeah
yeah where's the personal part of this
training meant to be coming in yes
exactly this and it's also like a weird
one because like when you when you
actually train Bunches of people you it
kind of looks like you're doing the same
stuff you are going to choose from the
same battery and exercise that is with
slight Nuance based on who the person is
yeah I'd say lengths of the body and
like biomechanics and also their
preferences what they've done before
what they want to do in future as well
so I have that like you know when I've
got a group of four girls training
together right one of them is going to
do a back squat the other one's gonna do
a front squat and the third one
slight nuances because one has a very
long femur the other one you know hasn't
have as much of a rotation and I hit for
example or whatever you know or it's
just you know doesn't feel comfortable
in a back school you just went by some
front squat because second preference
just comes into play right yeah so if my
client comes in if I have programmed in
my back spot for example but I have done
in five two months for example then they
go hey I haven't done transport for a
while could we do that it's like yeah
sure yeah why not yeah but if you're
gonna do that we're gonna stick with it
for X period of time so you can actually
yeah what I'll do this this week and
then again in 16 weeks and hope there's
some change there's some change yeah
exactly
um but yeah the expectation is that you
need to die every single session or
being super sore around yeah but you
know the fact is that like when you
start training when you're competing
you'll be like how many weeks are you so
four or five tops maybe depending on how
you eat them yeah yeah and then suddenly
you just not saw anymore yeah right a
little bit like you have a little bit of
a hassle usually like I'm always
crippled with my hamstrings yeah
um but like you know I'll just yeah
um but like you know then you change up
a program a little bit you have a new
stimulus and your body gets sore again
because it's a new thing that you
haven't adapted to yet for example right
yeah
um but like yeah it's a funny
conversation to have with new people
when I tell them the first two weeks of
training it's gonna be me talking a lot
yeah and then it's suddenly gonna get
really hard yeah because I'm gonna be
talking a lot less
yeah and the sets are gonna increase and
the reps are gonna increase and the
weight is going to increase and then
you're gonna notice that yeah so um but
one thing I always tell people like this
isn't rocket science this isn't
complicated really you know like for
what you need to know to do this flight
and keep doing this for the rest of the
life you know for the rest of your life
you don't need to know everything about
this you just need to know what's right
for you and how to do this and when to
do this basically and then like if you
want to push it a bit harder then that's
up to you yeah really but that's that's
strangely it yeah I know it is once
people get that proprioception and
knowing right even though I'm not
looking at my hips I know the difference
between my hips being here and my spawn
being like this being there yeah once
you get that and your hard Progressive
overload and you have some sort of
critical thinking in terms of is this a
good idea to do a little overhead press
after I've done a lateral raise exactly
once you understand that it is as simple
as it needs to be for you exactly but
yeah like I say it's not multiple it's
not sexy it's exactly yeah so that's the
master don't say so it's definitely hard
right it's hard work yeah if you're
wrong it's not always nice you don't
always love every workout like sometimes
you go with and you go I don't really
want to be here yeah
um and like I hated this uh dishonesty
you know Fitness where everybody acts
like they love every single minute in
their dream yeah it's not true we know
it's not true we have worked with
athletes you know like I work with a
pretty high level people like you know
who sometimes are cursing me out you
know and I know people who love it who
genuinely love it and they turn that
because they're a bit more stressed in
the head a bit less deeper they've been
dealing with something else basically in
just a particular session just feels
like [\h__\h] yeah and it is like that
sometimes you know or you have people
become oh yeah I have to get my head
down and grind and go to war in this
house it's not that serious Yeah it's
you're not in a trenches mate it's just
a workout no you just probably want to
be a bit healthier and look better naked
like it's not more serious than that and
like even even with people who like play
contact Sports basically right you tell
them like I I I caught my old coaches a
lot
um so I sounded really smart ways
because I can train by really smart
people
um the dumbest thing you can do if
you're an athlete is to get hurt in a
gym yeah yeah because then you can play
exactly yeah that's the opposite of what
you're trying to achieve yeah this is
supposed to supplement you help you run
faster jump higher throw further
basically you know or be more stable to
them you're broken if somebody runs into
you and tackles you yeah but you're not
meant to destroy yourself on the bench
press or blow your knees out doing
something that you're not going to be
doing right yeah so especially then I
really hate it when people are like yeah
they're gonna train like an athlete and
they do some fleeting right now like a
clown crack basically on a stability
ball basically when you're just like why
yeah what what part of your Athletics is
that gonna translate are you wrong on
the pitch are you running on the water
but exactly yeah
so um you know but um people obsessed
with specificity a lot because everybody
likes to have a gimmick right in
training yeah and everybody is like oh
yeah you need to do it that way and this
way is the one way and this way is the
other way and like there isn't one way
no there just isn't that whatever goal
you have unless you are very very
specific right so if you're a power
lifter
squad's deadlift patch and whatever
helps you with assistance with that
right that's all you're doing yeah
that's generally all you're doing yeah
and that's your sentence until you
retire to do those three lifts and maybe
six other exercises on rotation yeah
right because you do two hour sessions
that literally contain three movements
it's the most boring thing on the planet
and your life and your value and
everything is dictated on your
performance emotions exactly right and
and
you guys are great yeah um but for
people who just going into the gym and
they're trying to move a bit better and
feel a bit stronger and maybe look up it
but uh you know just generally have a
easier life basically and not having the
back hurt when they're sitting down
right it's just since a completely wrong
message because it tells them oh you
want to have a strong back you need to
do one red Maxes on a deadlift you don't
you really don't and you can see how
someone new to a gym would connect with
dots in a sense that I'm lifting this
much I want to get stronger look at this
guy he's really strong strong let's do
what he does and it's like he's very
strong for a specific set of things yeah
and so if you just want to get strong
for General everyday life then maybe
have a look at hexbar maybe pick up like
a Monster bench press or a safety bar
and these sorts of things yeah like you
know you don't have to do those
movements just because somebody else is
doing them right yeah and even then even
then like if you're like literally not
an athlete who you know performs in
volleyball sports basically right yeah
if the CrossFit power lifter or anything
right yeah pick stuff that you enjoy
doing yeah because if you don't enjoy
doing anything I'm gonna do it not for a
while no no you'll do this for a few
months and you're gonna go I hate this
this is graduated so if you feel like
crap my shoulders feel uncomfortable
this that and they are there like I said
you know they were neutral grip bench
press or if you don't like bench press
or dog you don't have to do this bench
press perfectly fine price ups are fine
you can add a bunch to them you know you
can do dips if you prefer that you can
rotate them around you can just
completely avoid this stuff right yeah
like yeah you need to be able to push
pull horizontal vertical and hinge and
some squid variation because that's what
your body evolved to do yeah but you
don't have to be the best box water on
the planet no no once you understand
those movement patterns you understand
they can be applied in well with
whatever tools you want whether it's a
TRX or cable a dumbbell exactly yeah
yeah absolutely so um it's partially
because the people who we
kind of present the most as like oh this
is Fitness right this is what Fitness is
it's like bodybuilders or Elite power
lifters basically and it's like but
those people are so far removed from
general population both in the wants and
their needs and the genetics yeah as
well because like people don't like to
listen to that really and like it's kind
of both ways as well because you'll get
people who go yeah I don't go to the gym
because my genetics are shared it's like
you don't even know what your genetics
are because you never tried yeah right
and and like even if you're not gonna
end up being Mr Olympia like you can
still get stronger and not be in pain
and still look a bit better and feel a
bit better yeah and you know
um you you don't need to be those people
but unfortunately when somebody you know
has uh first contact with Fitness is
usually going to be bodybuilders yeah
right and like when you actually look at
people who go to gyms bodybuilders are
not there they make up a tiny tiny
percentage of people and I'm not not
talking about people who think they're
bodybuilders I mean legitimately people
who go and compete and do the prep and
everything else basically that's the
smallest tiniest percentage of people
who actually go to the gyms yeah and if
you see one in the Germans because he
probably had to squeeze it after work
because he's actually going to a natural
bodybuilding so yeah that has the
specific equipment that they need to be
using right yeah so it's just very
misleading of how it's being portrayed
because like in reality it's like yeah
you shouldn't be doing resistance
training but there isn't one way of
doing it or just like one goal being to
be striving towards like I've got people
who enjoy training because they like how
it makes them feel and how it makes them
move and they completely don't care
about how they look you know and it's
absolutely fine yeah absolutely fine
even if you're just doing this because
you're coming in for the bands because
you like the people you're training with
and you're just doing this casually
because like at that point to tell me I
wouldn't come here if you weren't here
yeah but I know it's good for me so I
keep turning out right and it's
absolutely fine it's absolutely fine but
then you go on Instagram
and it's going to be a guy with no
t-shirt on the heart backwards I should
have had my yeah
being like if you don't love it you
don't belong here you don't really want
it it's like I'm gonna say you're a 24
year old who spent the last five years
in a gym with no social life no hobby no
nothing this is literally all you do and
you're gonna tell a mother of all free
with a full-time job who has to commit
to work from a nr7 to nr1 like she's
lazy yeah always she needs to sleep more
it's like don't you think she's full of
that like don't you think yeah yeah like
oh you're not dedicated in that one like
people are dedicated enough yeah right
that this is not their priority they
want to find a way to get something out
of this basically they're not trying to
compete with you no they want to balance
it well the other [\h__\h] they're worried
about it exactly yeah exactly and like a
lot of people in Fitness miss it and a
lot of people who are trying to get into
it that's what they are being you know
thrown at the face effectively and it
really puts them off yeah and and that's
how we you know end up having gyms that
have a lot of members in them but it
doesn't help anyone yeah you know
nobody's getting better everybody's
getting discouraged from creation you're
ever again whatever because the way is
being presented by those people and
unfortunately the louder you shout the
more about what you make out of yourself
the more likes you're gonna get yeah
yeah um so you know there's sensible
advice they will be like you know calm
and collected and actually hey you know
you need to focus on your Basics and to
focus on your bracing I would rather you
lie down on the floor and focus on
pushing your lower back into the floor
while breathing into your diaphragm
right this is like the face thing that
should be thought before you even touch
the bubble basically yeah you're not
gonna see that on Instagram yeah you're
gonna see people you know doing knee
raises or getting punched in the ribs
you know yeah or some kind of glue
Kickback with barely any clothes or yeah
all the kit and the headband and
everything from around as much weight as
I can exactly and you know we've seen
this people coming with very expensive
knee sleeves you know
um and yeah it's just a gimmick it just
becomes an absolute gimmick you know the
same way um people will make anything
completely the identity it's like this
um commodification of identity I think
is the term basically where like you
don't train you to CrossFit yeah you
don't suggest you're a power lifter you
need to have this gear you need to wear
this brand you know it's like it just
becomes almost this like cult basically
and it's not it
Fitness Industries and Industry
industry's job is to make money yeah
right it just likes to say that it's
helping people and he does you know he
doesn't say that we like somehow you
know commenting the tremendous people or
not but people have to make money people
have to make money and there is a lot of
people in the industry who's Main and
only concerned is to make money yeah and
they don't care about anything else and
they found a way they they found a
message that resonates with people that
they can you know listen for a couple of
months before they drop off
exactly yeah well you know in most cases
it's going to be some guy like mistress
on YouTube who's gonna tell people about
their body types and some other types
and stuff in my [\h__\h] work out you
know yeah yeah and that's usually we'll
be competing with at the moment right
because the thing with properties is
people very quickly figure out the big
Rapides yeah and they don't have lines
oh yeah that's the thing like even when
we were working in like one of the
bigger commercial gyms in the city seven
thousand members yeah yeah Peaks about
seven thousand and there was what was
there 15 of us
12 to 15 yeah and you'd look at that in
here right there's 15 personal trainers
I want to see 15 people all the time and
really you just see like three or four
of us there most of the time yeah yeah
three or four people there half the time
yeah and three or four people like clean
machines basically exactly but you know
but before things like that there was a
lot of entitlement they train you an
entitlement right because we we have new
known and worked with people who looked
amazing yeah right who literally look
like Greek statues basically but they
were so disparaging towards everybody
who wasn't like them that they put no
care whatsoever well that's the thing
I've I've had friends and like
colleagues and stuff before who as they
get qualified it's like so what's your
demographic who you're going to work
with and like people like me
have you ever had a coach have you ever
gone to the grocery like no I don't need
one hello so how are you gonna how are
you gonna sell how are you gonna like
communicate this
I don't know and they're the people who
get qualified and they think right I'll
go work in history and there'll be 20
people lined up on my first day to pay
me and start working with me I'm gonna
oil up and take some pictures holding
dumbbells with my t-shirt off and the
people are gonna throw money I promise
yeah line up there's 10 other people
like you exactly yeah bigger more
experienced more impressive taller
better looking just because they're
prettier yeah especially nowadays since
everyone has gone online since the
pandemic everyone wants online coaching
used to be a thing that some people
would do and some people would be like
no I'm purely in person but most people
are contactable connectable across the
world now exactly you are not going to
be the person who wins that game like
the oiliest most lean ABS basically
exactly because it's actually this
because like you know like I I did it I
didn't know in the winter when I wanted
to learn a little bit more and I
literally got in contact with people
from RB strength yeah
whatever to make myself a program right
yeah I I have access to somebody like
this now I'm not gonna go to a a random
bro in a gym who just sits staring at
the Tupperware and ever walks of anybody
if I can literally get somebody who's
got a doctorate in human physiology yeah
and it's been training top of the world
athletes basically right if that's what
I'm looking for I can go to somebody
like this yeah right but um yeah so it's
kind of good that those people do get
weeded out because we have seen so many
come and go yeah um but also
unfortunately
um people do get fooled yeah people get
lost along the way yeah yeah they don't
come in and they look at this guy and
they go wow if he does look amazing he
must know what he's talking about it's
like yeah he does in how to make himself
look that way yeah that's it that's all
they know that's all they've ever done
and chances are that person spending so
much time on themselves and making
themselves a certain way they might not
have overtime or Compassion or empathy
in the world to get loads other people
to do the exact same yeah unless you
literally want a step-by-step guide of
what they're doing which doesn't work
for myself no of course not like I I
would never like I train differently now
with my late 30s and I used to do my 20s
obviously
yeah I don't foreign
ly did I did those like Redline workouts
basically a lot of the time you know
because I really really enjoyed it but I
would never make my clients with this
stuff no no sometimes they like I told
them about something I want to show them
something just like hey do you want to
see something cool you know
um last week uh I would make I I'll make
guys do a row with a sled oh yeah
because I used to do one of my favorite
exercises and I used to train myself
yeah in my old room right
um so I thought like hey guys this isn't
this really cool exercise we could try
because I have a sled and I have a rope
we can just do that today as a pool you
know Amazon row right and we did that
and then one of them said can you make
it any worse
just
so we did the prone row which is you
know a plank row on the sled and that
was at 50 kilo sled okay so yeah that's
legit then yeah right and like I can do
this I haven't done this in a very long
time but I can maintain Plank and I can
talk while doing this right so they see
me do this and I go yeah I can totally
do this and then pulled once and they go
oh [\h__\h] you know you can't do this to
people you can't expect people to train
like you do if you're a bodybuilder
you're a physic athlete who you know
competes and you like you will push to
the point when your pump is splitting
your skin basically the next guy who
just started who came to you because he
wants to believe you you're just gonna
put them off yeah you're just gonna make
them feel inadequate yeah and it's
something to your better you've just
done it for longer yeah and also the
things that get you to that stage are
not necessarily the things yeah yeah
exactly no different if someone like
turned up to any kind of course or I
always use universities like the option
for people to understand this but you
don't write your dissertation in your
first year you do very different things
in your first year to Second To Third to
build you up to the final and fitness
should be no different right exactly you
don't need to look at someone that's
where I want to be what they're doing
today is what I should be doing today
but yeah people don't necessarily see
that first thing and people don't always
explain it the best way exactly so like
if anybody who like you know isn't a
Pity is going to be watching this right
like do how much you feel like you want
to be doing you don't have to do what we
do right because I used to be that guy
who I would be 7am I also mentioned
calling the owner why isn't the gym
opening it you know to the point
legitimately they get so pissed off with
me they cut me my own key
so I used to work in the ee customer
service like the service finished work
at 11. my wife would come down from
Tabby stuck in a car to pick me up we
would go to the gym by like midnight and
sit there till two o'clock in the
morning really because yeah because we
were restless so we had to do this
because we had a show on the weekend
we're driving from Plymouth to Norwich
to do you know two days three days so
first thing show and training and then
coming back swapping Red Bull Canton ice
box because you know I couldn't drive
from Pain basically you know seven hours
and back to work and back to the gym at
1am right I did that because I loved it
and that's what I wanted to do and it
was a specific code that I was trading
at and then when I stopped wrestling
well guess what I stopped doing
because like you know I still enjoy her
training I still been doing this you
know difficult stuff basically because I
had fun doing it yeah but now I'm doing
this because I have fun with it yeah not
because I'm trying to get something out
of it I'm trying to maintain my strength
maintain my health maintain my physique
basically I'm happy with how things are
I'm not trying to PR I'm not trying to
pretend I'm a power lifter I'm not
trying to impress anybody you know I
don't want to break but exactly I just
don't want to break but that's just like
one one thing that you you know we've
mentioned it a few times over the years
that something that neither me or you do
um we don't really post ourselves
without clothes off no right because
it's not fair it's not the service
either no yes exactly and it's like you
know I've done along done this for a
while basically and I do have pretty
good genetics I can't pretend that I'm
not basically because like I can't tell
somebody who comes in to work with me
like hey look at this picture of me I'm
gonna make you look like this it's like
no you're not six foot nine yeah you
don't come from a family of six foot
something monsters who all play
basketball if there's some boxes and
that was my family you know so for me
this stuff comes probably a little bit
easily for most other people and it's
just not fair for me to to show off and
be like hey come and pay me because I'm
hot yeah no pay me because I will show
you how to do this so you can do this to
split your goals and your lifestyle and
not hate yourself yeah and not break
yourself I think that's the thing a lot
of people Miss is that people who you
said being a personal trainer wasn't
something you ever thought of and it
wasn't even really for me it was
something that someone else suggested
but I go and do and I was like no it's
not it's not reliable income I'm not
really interested I just like training
for me basically but then you do realize
that training for you and training for
someone else is too very you know
incredible things absolutely and there
are some really great coaches out there
who aren't necessarily in the best shape
but it doesn't take away from the fact
that they can't coach someone else to do
it exactly um and people always throw
around that time oh your body's your
business card it's not I understand to a
degree that for someone to be able to
elicit response in someone else they
want to at least elicit themselves first
or to a certain degree at some point
first however we've worked with enough
people that look like fitness models and
they're shy pts yeah and it's just like
that it's not those two things are not
the same no no basically it's not to say
that everybody who's super great looking
is a [\h__\h] pity I know because we've met
some really really good ones as well
um but like there is a sense of
entitlement with that unfortunately that
comes a lot and you know a lot of the
time people genuinely think that but
also um
the same way Fitness is portrayed to
people like I said earlier like oh
bodybuilders and powerlift there's a
super strong super impressive people who
are like the top percentage basically
the way the industry is advertise the
potential pts is equally Twisted yeah
right because like we we still get those
Southwest right it's like hey yeah
there's a very handsome dude leaning
over this very fit girl in short shorts
and like you're gonna earn 70k a year
yeah no and like you know like I do okay
when I'm like very busy basically but
like but I used to do like 12 hours 13
hour days you know like I got to at one
point to the point when I got so ill I
started coughing blood in front of my
clients you know that was the moment I
was like what the [\h__\h]
yeah you know so like yeah sure you
can't make quite a lot by the end of the
day there's only that many hours of
getting a day yeah and you certainly
won't do it early on like I always say
to you but first you think like an
apprenticeship if you count up the hours
you'll put in and the money you'll
receive it it might be around minimum
wage but like realistically you building
those up yeah you work hard in the first
year or so to build your client base up
and then once it's there you still work
to keep it running you've got at least
the money flows a bit more than where it
doesn't initially it definitely took me
I would say a year before I was like oh
man okay this is actually a job yeah I
don't have to allow you know it really
counts my pennies basically and whatever
and then like maybe two years in is when
I was like okay I'm getting this now
I've got the world of mouth I've got my
testimonials I've got some results
basically people are happy I've got a
client base that stays with me because
they enjoy trading with me but it took a
lot of work yeah um not just you know
sitting in a staff room stirring to the
Tupperware and complaining because
people don't want to throw money at you
exactly yeah because I used to do this
game
um
yeah yeah
because like you just actually need to
go and do it you actually need to talk
to people and show them the UK and like
you know offer some advice you know yeah
like you don't even have to go and tell
them straight away you're going to give
them a session just say hey I saw you do
I get a little swing but did you happen
to show me how to do this a little bit
better yeah right they'll be very very
happy okay and then you see them again
maybe maybe I'll come all the time again
free we'll have a look what we've got
yeah and then if they want to work with
you they do if they don't no pressure
they might come back three months down
the line but by their new spoken to 10
other people at that point and someone
else has and also about that time you've
already had that person two other times
they're gonna come to the gym with their
friends they're gonna tell them hey this
guy help me go ask him for advice you
know or somebody else is gonna sign up
with them in a few months you know we'll
go into the first day and I'll go hey
Martin you helped me a few months ago
could you help my friend yeah this is
this is literally they're not going to
send their friends to the guy or girl
yeah what was me
oh my God oh God
I'm sorry I stopped myself because
they're too obvious of who will be
talking about this thing but I I you
know I've watched people kick off
because I don't want to do this [\h__\h]
class I'm too good for this it's like
your class is weak nobody wants to do it
because you don't care and everybody can
tell you're miserable yeah there's a
reason why it's not working yeah yeah
and I think that's part of it too is
that some people will come into the
industry book their first few sessions
or get a full book of clients but then
not reinvest the time and or money to be
like right now I'm working with this
many people I need a decent service for
them I need to either like some really
[\h__\h] hot spreadsheets or an app or
something they can log on their progress
I need some kind of capsule for people
who I help they don't necessarily want
my paid help right now but they can come
back to me later for exactly and all
these other services that you need to
build out as well as having that skill
with people on the gym floor because I
think yeah plenty of people come in get
their first few cards book in and then
just kick the seat up and be all right
30 pounds an hour 20 sessions a week I'm
done last 20 hours or it's not 20 hours
a week
exactly exactly
um unfortunately you like that that job
doesn't work very well with social life
no okay so life in general well yeah
because you people are only going to
train when they're not online so your
work becomes when people are not at work
this is this is the one
um how well you have PT you'll basically
live at the gym must be very easy to
train for you and it's like mate I
genuinely have clients who play medical
system because I am yeah because they
just don't have the time and like I
would love to get back into grafting for
example and like it's physically
impossible for me because whenever I
look at this you know sessions are six
o'clock seven o'clock yeah guess what
I'm working with my clients six o'clock
seven o'clock right yeah and you only
get a few of those hours in a day when
you you know you you know you're gonna
have people yeah right it seems like
you've got 12 hours throughout of the
day but realistically there's going to
be a lot of gaps in the middle there's
ammonia lunchtime and evening yeah and
like you know how
again is this hashtag ground hustle I'm
in a trenches you're not in Adventures
you are a t-shirt to work man yeah
one of the more cushy day today
absolutely absolutely every day I tell
myself I've got the best job in the
plant you know like I I get to wear a
metal bands t-shirt to walk I can wear a
tracksuit and trainers I can talk about
horror movies in the bands I've listened
to my clients mate what other job can
you do that to me yeah exactly you know
like and people are making markets up to
themselves basically it's like oh yeah
no man I'm telling the trenches I'm on
the front lines oh man you never walk
her life a day in your life yeah yeah
you're working in a gym based around a
passion and a hobby of yourself
on board and you don't have a [\h__\h]
boss to reply to exactly exactly but
yeah people want to make Masters out
themselves really yeah and I don't
understand why this everybody is just
trying to look more part down and you
know but like it's also annoying because
it's such a posturing basically it's
like yeah I'm grinding and I'm hosting
so no you're not you're literally on
your phone cracking the Tupperware in
staff room all day yeah yeah I don't see
you grinding yeah I don't see the
results of any of anything of you doing
I don't see any reviews your Instagram
profile is full of pictures of you yeah
you'll keep talking about your personal
training about who are you training
where are all those people you're
training yeah where are those people
talking about you where is you showing
the world that you're doing right uh
it's um it's really annoying um
I do occasionally talk to Young
adjectives right that they'll ask me
it's like hey you know I can see you're
a bit busy and how you're doing it like
and some will get it they're like this
isn't about you yeah like you don't
matter yeah like it's it's your clients
that matter this is the outcome of your
work this is what's going to bring you
more clients not what you look like not
what's your flailing workout looks like
not you doing some Tick Tock dance or
whatever the challenge of the week is
basically like that none of this matters
to anybody yeah
um you might get some likes but those
people aren't customers those are people
who want your service exactly it's like
they're trying to um they worry too much
about impressing other pts and they
don't just fall into this trap of like
oh we need to outdo each other on this
completely unnecessary [\h__\h] and they
completely just ignore the fact that
they're there to actually help people
yeah and that's what the job is to
actually help people yeah
um so it's a difficult one because we
there should be a lot more really good
BTS but there really isn't no no sadly
and we have seen people who were very
very very good but they might have
lacked confidence for example to
actually go and get those clients yeah
or you know imposter syndrome is
horrible especially when you're actually
good at this that you tend to have a lot
more of that right yeah and we have seen
people who were absolutely god-awful
they just happen to end up looking
relatively good basically and just like
stuck out somehow for multiple years
basically God knows how yeah
um I normally say who is it's a
combination of having some sort of
knowledge Imaging and knowing how to
give a person a certain exercise or a
certain exercise program to listen a
certain response
personality is a big one as well
generally like if people don't share
similar Hobbies or interests with you
that I was going to feel a hell of a lot
longer than an hour absolutely yeah um
but then also like you said your
marketing and your ability to actually
run a business if you can't nail all of
those to a certain degree then it is
going to show up and it is going to
negatively affect you but you need to
know you might be better at one thing
than the other absolutely everybody
nobody's great at everything right no
but like I hate making social media
content for example
you know but I know that this is
something I should be doing more of
exactly it's a necessary part of the
layer isn't it yeah yeah I hate it there
are some people who absolutely love it
the love making you know reels and
whatever basically I'm just like
oh God okay yeah I've got those four
written out but I was supposed to do two
months ago I better take the camera out
to the gym and film it and then when I
actually posted people have no idea how
much swearing goes on yeah I'm trying to
get to spin the right way yeah like I
actually know how to do video editing as
well right and everything like that like
that part isn't difficult for me it's
just the fact of like oh my God
but it's already 50 000 other videos to
be the exact same thing I'm doing I'm
doing but I need to I hate myself and
other people yeah
so uh yeah it's it's a really weird one
it's a really weird one especially when
you see people who like started up a
long time ago and they got stuck in that
mindset of like late 90s early 2000s and
they just completely refused to ever
change anything and just move on with
how things are changing in the industry
you know yeah yeah
um would you say your workouts in terms
of what you give to your clients has
changed much in terms of how you used to
train people when you first qualified to
where you're at now
not really actually yeah
um so I I I I was so my work has to
always dictated with how much people can
actually do within a week yeah okay so
um it turns out that shock horror most
people can't all don't want to be in a
gym four or five times a week okay even
if they do they probably won't pay you
to be there with you four or five times
a week yeah you can't afford it like
what we are not providing a ship service
you know let's let's be honest with you
this isn't something that a lot of
people can afford right so um but like I
always try to actually make sure so my
priority always was to make sure that
people actually get the money swap right
so I would tell people like look um if
you can only try and talk two times a
week we need to make sure that you can
do the movements that your body can do
right so like I mentioned earlier
push-pull horizontal vertical okay and
it's just
details have changed maybe really but if
you have multiple people going to
sessions a week you're not going to
reinvent the wheel that much and I don't
I never had like a style of training
um if I make people do something that I
enjoy
um you know because I do sometimes I
don't also want to have fun and I am a
bit of a sadist yeah
um you know it's always in the case of
would you like to try this we've been
doing this for a very long time would
you like to see how far you can take
this oh you hate Smith schools would you
like to show me to show you how horrible
you can mix this course yeah look at
this next step along yeah yeah yeah I
can show you what you can build up
towards basically right but no I want
them to cover the basics I wanted to
make sure that they're moving well and
then if they're progressing they keep
going then you can change it up a bit
further but
um it was it was the guy who was to
introduce with me uh remember which but
he was saying that it sounded a lot
scarier but he used to say there is only
that many ways you can bend the human
joint yeah yeah and it's true already
there's only that many ways you can bend
the elbow or Flex the knee or you know
hinge your hip basically like that it's
not really
[Music]
your squats your pushes and your pulls
it is just finding a way to balance it
all out in a training program then
balances with a person's life right and
it'll be trial and error anyway because
you might recommend two sessions a week
and they only do one or you recommend
two and they're like
a third you know so you're programmed
two with a third optional one so that's
where you get to play with a little
family to work out yeah yeah exactly
normally like an arm and a cordless yeah
yeah
this is literally this so I've gone guys
we'll start up to two days a week and
then you know after a while they were
like oh I could do a little bit more I'm
like okay well you know you understand
that we need more volume you know if you
want to get your hands bigger for
example in your shoulders look at the
bigger whatever now you understand it
you need more sets if you need more reps
and whatever the only way we can do that
is by adding another day yeah so let's
sacrifice one of those midweek sessions
to teach you another workout that you
can do by yourself and then come back to
me until extern you're going to show
that again and see how everything on
with that and that's when you start
adding I say to people sometimes like
they are exercises then I don't want you
to be paying me to be standing next to
you watching you do this yeah right I
don't want people to spending money so
that I can stand next to them eat my
hand washing them walk on a treadmill
yeah exactly what are you doing with
people's time stop doing this yeah right
like if they need that ask them to turn
off five minutes early and do I warm up
on the treadmill or ask them to walk
through the gym rather than drive up
basically or whatever right or you
should be able to prepare a five minutes
Mobility drill to make sure that they
actually loosen up a bit you know make
them throw a slam ball on the floor a
little bit you know or whatever just
make something very very simple not to
waste their time yeah basically and like
the amount of seeing people being like
Oh Yeah well my phone is coming in I'm
gonna spend 10 minutes with them on the
treadmill then we're gonna do some
[\h__\h] that when I'm stretching easy
and it's like people can tell yeah they
might not tell for the first month yeah
but after a while they will especially
if they're gonna be there with you
another somebody else running with
another trainer who actually makes them
do stuff and they're gonna put two and
two together and be like hang on a
second yeah right
um and it is bad it's bad for people
because
um they're not getting what they're
paying for uh they could discourages
them and it also makes all of us look
like absolute tools yeah because it's
ringing like if you're in a dream of
multiplicities it takes one to do
something stupid for that person to then
go away and say all pities are [\h__\h] yeah
yeah like people are so much more likely
to tell people about negative experience
they have about the positive one and
we've been in those situations yeah
where people have cost complaints in the
dream and we all had to take [\h__\h] for it
basically because one [\h__\h] decided to
free somebody for 50 times yeah right
um
although you know that I thought to
myself earlier when I was coming here uh
it made myself laugh right because I was
like I need to be careful with how much
details I'm pushing those stories
because I don't really want to you know
be with people yeah but at the same time
I realized that please
basically not just even that people who
would be offended by me saying the
things I'm saying are not the type of
people who spend an hour doing something
productive like listening to a podcast
in the first place
yeah it's very true you know like I've
never seen any of those people that like
I think about right now and you probably
have a couple of names in your head
right yeah I've never seen them sit down
with a book yeah right yeah like when me
and you used to work together and we had
a few mates like Craig and Alex for
example and whatnot and a couple of
others like we would like hey have you
seen this have you tried this oh I've
saw you do this can I go with you on the
side and try that together or like I
used to like swap sessions together yeah
you know like I would have like um
Rebecca come over and be like hey can I
see how you're training and spend a
session with you for example let them
hate me because she couldn't knock it
out before 90 days you know
um and and and there are people who are
trying you know who are trying to learn
and they you know actually inquisitive
and then there is unfortunately quite a
bit of people who are just like I know
everything now yeah it doesn't matter
you know your [\h__\h] anyway you like I
don't understand yeah yeah people just
don't understand the help I can give
them yeah it was really funny like I I
can tell this one story actually because
it's really funny and I don't if the guy
I don't think exists
um but I I worked with a guy who's so I
hated doing gym classes by the way so
for people who are general public or you
go into the dream or you think you're
going to the gym uh gym class is a
[\h__\h] they really are
um because you can't make them good in a
busy commercial gym you know when you've
got a class like 20 like yeah yeah and
also you'll never know who's gonna turn
up yeah okay so you might have a couple
of regulars you have seen around the gym
called you know the agent plus Heroes
who are turning up every single session
there are people like this okay and they
generally already know how to do certain
things okay but then you might prepare
something that's quite challenging and
you're gonna have two people coming in
who go I'll just sign up to the gym I
thought I'll have a go there was a
customer system and you go oh I'm gonna
kill you
um so you and I try to get creative with
my classes and you remember I spent like
six months of refusing to do them yeah
well I just was like I'm not doing this
I'm not doing classes I'll do everything
else don't make me do classes and then
it changed and I had to do a class so I
thought right I hate this so much but
I'm gonna try to make a good class I'm
gonna try to make something so there's
some progression so some people who turn
back I'm gonna give them some options to
make it a little bit harder okay yeah
and the class that I did because I hated
doing them suddenly became very very
popular and there was another person
doing it just directly after me I
remember this one because you have your
own story of the guy
um who nobody would do his classes
because they're a garbage you know if
you just make some like step UPS in a
tiny box basically or whatever and she
was a super fancy bodybuilder he finds
it for myself right yeah
um and then um because people were
unhappy with these classes uh I got
asked through another one because one
was fully booked and people were
actually complaining that they can't get
on my class so I said to management
right well you know I want to shift
anyway I've got time to kill because you
know you're kind of bored after you've
done a cleaning you then you're talking
you get to like seven eight o'clock
there really isn't that many people to
talk to anyway yeah also you're probably
tired you want to go home yourself like
let's be honest people pickies get tired
and the caffeine addiction is serious
yeah
um I ended up having another class in
like straight away I got fully books and
I'm getting two bucks a pack and
then charge for my classes and I was
like dude I don't I don't care about
charging those two pounds from those 10
people basically because we had a notion
of charging right yeah so I don't care
I'm just doing this to kill time and do
something fun with people basically do a
couple of different exercises they might
have done on other classes like this is
this is just for fun yeah this is just
to give something people and because I
have to do this in this dream yeah and
this is the guy who had no clients
whatsoever nobody wanted to walk with
him and he sent me this long ass essay
super upset because I don't want to take
his advice and I'm like who the [\h__\h] are
you you took this time and actually put
it into writing some good copy and put
into your landing page or just talking
to somebody on the gym floor just doing
something but he had this like one
laminated transformation and he kept
clutching onto basically that he's done
at some point basically which I hate
transformation
yeah because it doesn't tell the full
story it doesn't tell a cool story and
also if you manage to get somebody like
so I have a client that you're teaching
right now yes okay cool it's done
phenomenally after trading with me but
it's like she's done everything
everything Food Training never skip the
session you know it's got a home gym
which helps yeah obviously right it's
really really hard looks phenomenal got
really strong you know it's like she
occasionally will send me a before and
after that I was sure because like
that's like an actual amazing before and
after right yeah but it will be unfair
for me to take that print it out to a
girl who's gonna come in on a Tuesday
for a consultation and be like I'm gonna
make you look like this this could be
you yeah right because the chances she's
not going to want to do it like that she
is not gonna want to like actually make
sure that she gets the right protein
count all the time she might not want to
put up with as much discomfort and
tiredness as my other client does for
example and it's fine yeah it's
absolutely fine and even if she did the
exact same thing from point A to Z
basically that the other person did it's
still not guaranteed that she would do
it the same way yeah it's still not
guaranteed that she would get us a
Celine or just as big or just as strong
because that's just not human body works
basically so I just see this as a super
unfair because you'll get those couple
of people who will do very very very
well but then you make everybody else
feel like [\h__\h] because they feel
inadequate yeah because they go that
person achieved that but I'm not
achieving it this must be my fault
because this super attract amazing good
looking personal trainer has clearly
achieved it with them so this must be me
being I'm lazy or whatever right and
people start beating themselves up about
it being right I'm doing something wrong
it's like actually not you're doing
everything right yeah you just have a
very different specific set of
circumstances are you offensive than you
were yesterday exactly and that's the
only comparison you need to make exactly
that so uh yeah it's just it's a really
really tricky one because it's it's not
something like it's probably gonna come
out a lot longer than you wanted it to
be we're already in an hour right that's
fine
as long as good
um it's not something that you can put
on an Instagram story yeah yeah like I'm
sure you're gonna try to like chop it up
or whatever basically but it's there's a
lot of nuance to it and obviously human
beings only once and everybody's
different and everybody has a different
story and everybody has different
struggles okay yeah like it's took me
you talk about empathy you mentioned it
earlier how important it is and it's
something that a lot of people
completely Overlook that you like even
if you can't put yourself into that
person's shoes like completely because
you don't have the same experiences then
you need to have respect for the story
and what they are yeah okay because like
I think it's
ah
it's difficult I think it's harder if
you're somebody who like you were always
healthy and you know you never had much
adversity in life when you were younger
and you started training at 16 and you
got to 18 and you look good and you've
got abs and you're big you know and you
go yeah everything's cool everybody's
got to say it as easy as I do but your
mom is doing a meal prep mate yeah yeah
you know like you don't understand that
somebody who lives with a partner who
might not be as supportive for the
courses then or somebody who doesn't
just do shopping for themselves because
they also have kids to feed for example
or somebody who's one day his job is
super stable but anything they can send
her for 14 hours across the country for
example and they're gonna have to buy
something in a Max and Spencer on a
Services basically yeah like people are
not the same and and very very very few
people at the luxury of being able to do
everything they want they imagine they
can do this yeah very very few and even
then you'll go through periods and
because again we're just humans right
you go for a moment where you go for a
hard breakup you go out from difference
for you know a difficult illness or you
have to change your job or whatever and
suddenly you can't afford a trainer
anymore right yeah like [\h__\h] like that
happens to people all the time and we
deal with this on a daily basis and you
need to understand that you need to know
that like people who are coming to you
people who go to the gym people who are
looking for help are not lazy lazy
people don't do it exactly lazy people
are not looking for help yeah basically
and I just absolutely hate it when I see
those literally brows it's always broken
off you look motivated enough motivation
is
are you motivated to brush your teeth
she'll be brushing your teeth because
now you're excited in two months and I'm
gonna be so excited yeah it's gonna be
November it's gonna be rainy cold dark
you're gonna leave work and it's gonna
be me I don't want to go to the gym yeah
I don't want to see the phone on the
hour by the time I get home it's going
to be half seven and a half eight I want
to sit down and have something warm to
eat watch Netflix and go to bed right
like this is what we are competing with
yeah it's Netflix
but you've got to instills people how
that's going to make them feel versus
skipping it and not doing it yeah right
so instead of telling people that you
know they are unmotivated lazy whatever
right which is just a horrible thing to
say to anybody which is um tell them
like hey if you would like go to the gym
and you didn't feel like it do three
sets yeah if you still hate it go home
yeah it's fine I've said to people
before when a lot of the times one of
the first questions being like what
supplement should I be taking I need a
pre-workout but I'm like if if a coffee
doesn't get you up for a work like a
strong black coffee doesn't get you up
for a workout as you need to be probably
breasts probably don't need to train
that day like just I literally
well my sleep is really [\h__\h] so I know
I've read it in elevates my cortisol and
I'm like say again the first part of
that sentence yeah
it's like why are you asking me about
the pill to counter cortisol when the
first thing you should be looking at is
why is you sleep [\h__\h] in the first place
yeah right yeah let's talk about what
time of a day do you have your last cup
of coffee like what is your before bed
habit are you falling asleep people
falling in your hands right do you have
a blackout lines in your room are you
falling asleep you play LED light
flashing someone on your eyes for
example because like and again this is
like no sexy stuff this is the stuff you
will not get the likes on and people
look at you and they go Oh I thought
you're gonna give me an advice you're
telling me to turn my [\h__\h] phone up
and it's like yeah
if that doesn't work then we can talk
like maybe you need some magnesium yeah
you know maybe there's some other stuff
we can try maybe your feeling you know
whatever basically like you mentioned
pre-workout basically as well which you
know that's a completely different
everything
yeah but then you realize after a couple
of years most of it doesn't work yeah
it's three to five active ingredients
for each personal preference and and the
one that actually works as caffeine yeah
everyone already takes anyway yeah yeah
exactly so it's like you know down
battery worker just get prop loss from
boots basically it's literally exactly
that yeah
um but that's good though I feel I would
talk to some covered a lot there what's
the best place to send people to to
impact your stuff and send people your
way
um so my website burnhamstrength.co.uk
um Instagram either one works fine
um drop me a message if you need any
advice if you don't need to want to
trade with me if you just want to ask me
for stuff whoever you're trying to get
into training go into PT
um you know I'm okay buy me a black
coffee if you want to you know get some
advice from me or whatever I will always
take free coffee from people
um and yeah no it was good it was good
it was time to actually do it yeah
oh we've actually managed to upset in
one
thanks for tuning in to find out more
from us hit the links in our description
for social medias or head to the website
which is integrityfitness.education
[Music]